Guide to the Individual manuscripts, publications, and artifacts, 150 AD. - 2014 MS2135
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Individual manuscripts, typescripts, artifacts, and images, MS2135 Series 1
  - Letter, Amos D. Hollistan to Sylvanus, 06/15/1852 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    This Presbyterian minister describes the moral and religious climate of Washington, D.C. as generally good, and is pleased with his religious work with poor blacks in the city. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1988. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Samuel Huntington to the President of Delaware [Caesar Rodney], 01/12/1780 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    Samuel Huntington, as President of the Continental Congress, writes to the President of Delaware (Caesar Rodney), transmitting a copy of an Act of Congress concerning provisions for the Continental Army. He asks that the states provide supplies for the needy army. James M. Brown, Professor of Law, and Margaret C. Brown gift, in honor of William Rankin Duryee, Emeritus Professor of Research Pathology, George Washington University School of Medicine (a descendant of Huntington) 1984. Formerly, Ind. Ms.
  - Roscoe Drummond, papers, 05/12/1956-03/25/1964 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    This collection contains items from the May 12, 1956 Gridiron Club Dinner. There are two draft copies of the speech "1956 Gridiron dinner speech in the dark." Also included is a program schedule, Mr. Drummond's name placard and dinner menu. Also included is Roscoe Drummond's personal Gridiron show book as president for the May 12, 1956 dinner. There are two letters one from the Secretary-General of the United Nations, dated November 27, 1964 and the other a letter in which, Edward Moore Kennedy accepts an invitation to the Gridiron Club reception, Apr. 26, 1964. Formerly Ind. Ms and HS 2725.W3 G83 1956.
  - Nine poems for children, 02/07/1954 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    Front page is a photocopy with the title "Nine poems for children" and a handwritten note that reads "Especially for Lydia Sincerely Langston Hughes Feb. 7, 1954" Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, F.R. Larkin to Editors of the Columbian Casket [and] obituary of T. Edwin Brown, 1867 ca.-01/27/1924 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    The letter, signed "Delta", concerns the proposed trip by Charles Dickens, 1867-1868, to the United States. Larkin fears that Dickens will present an unflattering picture of the U.S. in future writings. The obiturary if for T. Edwin Brown, alumnus of George Washington University. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Robert E. Lee to Elbert Turner, 11/02/1866 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    Robert E. Lee was the Commander-in-chief of Confederate forces during Civil War. This signed letter thanks Elbert Turner for election as honorary member in the Columbian College (now George Washington Univerity) Philophrenian Society. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Ronald Charles Lindsay to Cloyd Heck Marvin, 04/17/1930 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    In the letter Sir Ronald Charles Lindsay presents a copy of Ramsay MacDonald's American speeches. The letter was originally tipped in: McaDonald, James Ramsay. American speeches, DA566.9.M25A25 1930. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - A little girl's experience of the war, 1861 ca.-1865 -- --ca. (Box 5, Folder 59)
    Apparently written by a sister of Adele and Elsie Sherman. They may be the daughters of a Henry Sherman who was a clerk for the Treasury Department during and after the Civil War. The story is the description of a young girl's stay in Washington, D.C. during the Civil War. Mentions her sisters Adele and Elsie and a newborn brother. Describes a visit to the White House, seeing Abraham Lincoln, reactions to his assassination; Confederate prisoners escaping prison through their house; soldiers' marching; sick and wounded soldiers; several military alerts; her stays in several Washington boarding schools; victory parade at the end of the war. Ink inscriptions on first leaf: A.B. Sherman, E.M. Sherman, 813 Madison Avenue, NY City. Gelman Library purchased this item in 1994. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 104.
  - Letter, Belva A. Lockwood to Ulysses Clark, 12/08/1888 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    Belva Lockwood advocates woman suffrage, prohibition, arbitration, money and labor reform, and government control of railroads and telegraphs. She was the presidential candidate for the Equal Rights Party. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Order signed by Walter Lowrie as Secretary of the United States Senate, 12/24/1827 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    Manuscript document signed by Walter Lowrie as Secretary, ordering the referral to the Committee on the District of Columbia the nominations of Samuel Chase to by Judge of the Orphans Court, and David A. Hall and Thompson F. Mason to be Justices of the Peace. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Wilson Lumpkin to George Wood, 07/03/1830 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    Wilson Lumpkin served as a U.S. Congressman from Georgia, 1815-1817 and 1827-1831; U.S. Senator, 1837-1841; Governor of Georgia, 1831-1835. The letter describes his happy return to his family in Georgia; mentions he must soon decide if he will run again for Congress; mentions great popularity of President Andrew Jackson. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Curculio [manuscript fragment], undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
    Undated Latin manuscript. One page has title Curculio; the other, Comedia. In black ink with some notations in red and a decorated letter in blue. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Indenture between Ambrose Marechal and James F.M. Lucas, 10/07/1825 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    DS in which Marechal, as Archbishop of Baltimore, pledges land given to the Church by Daniel Carroll of Duddington, as security to cover debts that the Rev. James F.M. Lucas has incurred on behalf of St. Peter's Church of Washington, D.C Gelman Library purchased this indenture in 1984. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Catalog of books; Schedule A, 12/27/1827 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    List made in 1825 of about 1270 titles (3,034 volumes) of all the books in the Columbian College (later George Washington University) Library. This formed part of an inventory of the assets of the college made for creditors. According to E.L. Kayser's Bricks without straw (New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1970), Schedule A contained also a copy of an invoice of six cases of philosophical instruments, a general statement showing the value of each of the cases, and a complete inventory of the furniture and goods of the college. The ms. described here is only the book list, as the other parts are not with it. Title transcribed from front paper wrapper. Also known as: Catalogue of the books belonging to the Library of the Columbian College in the District of Columbia -- 1825. Also known as: Columbian College Library. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Contract, Benjamin More and William Cranch, 05/21/1796 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    Benjamin More was the publisher of the Washington Gazette, 1796-1798. Cranch was Chief Justice of the U.S. District Court of the District of Columbia, 1805-1855. This document is an agreement to carry on jointly a printing, bookselling, and stationer's business for five years. The expenses and profits are to be shared equally, although the business will be managed by More. Gelman Library purchased this document in 1987. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letters, Adolphe Moreau to "Cher Monsieur", undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
    Adolphe Ferdinand Moreau (1827-1882), art critic, writes to obtain information on Alexandre Gabriel Decamps, French painter and etcher. The April letter makes an appointment to get information on the brothers of Decamps; the December letter asks in what magazine a picture by Decamps appeared. Found in Moreau's Decamps et son oeuvre. Paris: D. Jouaust, 1869 (SPEC ND553.D29M8). Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, group of Washington citizens to the Mayor of Washington, D.C., 06/05/1822 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    The citizens recommend to the mayor, then Samuel N. Smallwood, that Solomon Hubbard be named market manager for the Center Market of the third ward of the city of Washington. The 32 signatures include those of Thomas Parsons and Peter Lenox. With address leaf. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1984. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letters, Iris Murdoch to Robin Waterfield, 11/09/1978-12/04/1981 (Box 5, Folder 69)
    Iris Murdoch (1919-) writes holograph notes to this antiquarian book dealer: 1978 Nov. 9, refusing a invitation; 1981 Nov. 8, refusing a request to write a preface to a book of poems; 1981 Nov. 20, describing herself as a "Buddhist Anglican"; and 1981 Dec. 4, briefly describing her religious beliefs. The letters are in chronological order. Gift, 1983, of J. William and Nina Matheson. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Stephen Olin to Thomas Sewall, 05/15/1845 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    Stephen Olin was a Methodist clergyman, president of Weslyan University, 1842-1851. The letter presents condolences to the Rev. Sewall upon the death of his father, Dr. Thomas Sewall, who was on the medical college staff of Columbian College (now George Washington University). Olin praises the medical care he received from Dr. Sewall. Provenance: Letter originally attached to paste-down of vol 1 of: The works of Stephen Olin. New York: Harper, 1852. Olin book with letter gift of Isabel Sewall. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Eugene O'Neill to Courtland Baker, 08/07/1930 ca. (Box 5, Folder 71)
    The letter expresses thanks for Prof. Baker's appreciation of two plays. Letter has handwritten note that Courtland Baker was an Associate Professor of Eng.[English] at The George Washington University. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Seth Pease to "Dear Sir", 09/01/1814 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    Seth Pease was a government surveyor and astronomer. Here he describes the capture of Washington by the British, Aug. 24, 1814, including destruction of public offices, and is uncertain whether more destruction will occur. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Seth Pease to "Dear Sir", 09/12/1814 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    Seth Pease was a government surveyor and astronomer. Following the capture of Washington by the British, Aug. 24, 1814, he predicts the removal of the seat of government from Washington. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Katherine Anne Porter to Dr. William L. Turner, 04/14/1965 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    In this letter, Katherine Anne Porter declines an invitation to lecture to Dr. Turner's classes at The George Washington University. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, A.B. Quinby to Mrs. Gen [Alexander] Macomb, 06/20/1824 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    The letter mentions Quinby's attempts to gain a position at the University of Pennsylvania; if unsuccessful at this, seeks to gain Mrs. Macomb's help in obtaining a faculty position in Washington, probably at Columbian College, now George Washington University. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Wethers Smith sent to Thomas J. Peacock, 05/06/1864 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    Wethers Smith was a Civil War soldier, probably in the Union Army. Smith, in this document sent to Thomas J. Peacock, authorizes Peacock to take temporary charge of his effects if he is killed, and if pickets prevent his son, Alfred Leigh, from reaching him. Witnessed by Ann Todd. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Muriel Spark to Margaret Stanley-Wrench, 11/02/1948 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    Muriel Spark (1918-), as General Secretary and Editor of the Poetry Review, refuses some poems submitted by Margaret Stanley-Wrench (1916-) J. William and Nina Matheson donated this to Gelman Library gift in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Joel Elias Spingarn to Elbridge Colby and poem by Joel Elias Spingarn, 03/17/1911 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    Joel Elias Spingarn was a literary critic and reformer; taught at Columbia University in New York, 1899-1911. The letter, with a typewritten poem enclosed, is signed by Spingarn and says he may someday publish a volume of verse. These items were found in Spingarn's: The new Hesperides, and other poems. New York: Sturgis & Walton, 1911. (PS3537.P66N4 1911). Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letters, Frank Sullivan to Milton Crane and Frank Sullivan to Peter Crane, 12/14/1959 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    Frank Sullivan was a humorist, writer for the New Yorker. The letter to Peter Crane concerning Peter's plans for a new magazine and his disapproval of overdevelopment of scenic areas. The letter to Milton Crane praising Peter Crane. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, E.G. Squier to J. W. Doughty, 10/15/1870 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    E.G.Squier was an author and diplomat, secretary, 1853, of the Honduras Interoceanic Railway. The letter advises recipient against seeking employment with the Honduras Interoceanic Railway Company. Originally the letter had a map enclosed: Map of Nigaragua: showing its departmental divisions and projected routes of interoceanic communication / by E.G. Squier. New York: Sarony & Major, 1851. (now in SPEC maps, G4850 1851 .S78). Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Charles Sumner to unnamed recipient, 07/08/1861 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    Charles Sumner was a senator. In the letter he agrees to recommend the recipient for a commission in the U.S. Army, but warns him of the large number of applicants for each commission. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Inscription, 12/19/1893 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    Inscription reads: "I so wish I were a little boy about 12 or 14 years old!" On paper reading: "22. Barkston Gardens, Earls Court S.W." Found in vol. 20 of Ellen Terry extra-illustrated Shakespeare, SPEC PR2753.H461 1901 f Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Mark Twain to "Dear Sir", undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
    Mark Twain, writing under his real name, Samuel Langhorne Clemens, refuses an invitation. The original catalog card indicates that the letter is dated between 1884-1910. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Charles Moore to Elihu Root and Arlington Memorial Bridge report, 09/07/1922-09/11/1922 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    The United States National Commission of Fine Arts was established in 1910. Typed letter signed by Charles Moore, chairman of the Commission of Fine Arts, to Elihu Root, enclosing a mechanically reproduced report concerned the location of the proposed Arlington Memorial Bridge. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Bush[rod] Washington to Walter Jones, 03/11/1806 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    As executor of George Washington's estate, B. Washington quotes from the President's will, in which he left his shares in the Potomac Company toward the establishment of a university in the District of Columbia. He then suggests to the congressman the passing of a law authorizing the use of the shares for the endowment of such a university. No educational institution ever received the benefit of the stock, however (Cf. E.L. Kayser. Bricks without straw, p. 13). Gelman Library purchased this letter from a dealer in 1981. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Richard W. West to Daniel Carroll, 08/13/1810 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    Richard W. West sends from his Maryland estate a note for the bank; address leaf calculations in Daniel Carroll's hand. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Charles Evans Whittaker to Roscoe Drummond, 03/06/1964 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    In the letter, Charles Evans Whittaker, retired Justice of the Supreme Court of the United States declines an invitation to the Gridiron Club dinner, Apr. 25, l964. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Memorandum to Tsar Nicholas II, undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
    An appeal to Tsar Nicholas II, probably in early 1917, by members of the special council of the Gosudarstvennyi? Sovet and the Duma, asking him to take under consideration the serious shortcomings in the Russian army as well as on the home front, with suggestions about what should be done to save the situation in order to continue the war. Found in George Washington University archives. Apparently used in a course on Russian history or economics. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Bill of sale, 11/28/1832 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    Benjamin Ogle Tayloe was the son of John Tayloe, builder of the Octagon House in Washington, D.C. Summary: Holograph document by which Tayloe, as executor of his father's estate,sells slaves, Emily and her daughter Catharine, to Emily's husband, the freed Charles Stuard, for $150.00. Signed by clerk William Brent, father of the first mayor of Washington. Gelman Library purchased this document in 1997. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Document, appointing James S. Chambers as the Navy agent for the Port of Philadelphia, 08/10/1861 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    Printed document with manuscript inserts, appointing James S. Chambers as the Navy agent for the Port of Philadelphia. Signed by Abraham Lincoln as President of the United States and Gideon Welles as Secretary of the Navy. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Document, by the President of the United States of America, 1861 ca. (Box 6, Folder 92)
    Ship's paper (printed form) with illustrations of a ship and of lighthouse at top of leaf, with signatures of Abraham Lincoln as President of the United States and William H. Seward as Secretary of State, but with no other manuscript inserts. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, Stephen Decatur to James L. Smith, 05/24/1818 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    Stephen Decatur was an American naval hero of the War of 1812. The letter apologizes for the delay in returning a paper signed by the mayor of Washington (Benjamin G. Orr). Attributes the delay to the difficulty of finding the mayor, who is involved in several business enterprises, including brickmaking. Gelman Library purchased this letter in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Washington Canal Company, papers, 1815-1821 (Box 6, Folder 94)
    The second Washington Canal Company, chartered in 1809, built the canal between 1810 and 1815. The company failed financially and was bought out by the city of Washington in 1831. These items Include ms. plan, 1815, April 11, of part of the canal; LS, 1821 Oct. 12, from Frederick May, President of the company, to Samuel N. Smallwood, Mayor of Washington, concerning continuation of a stone wall on the line of the canal, and a basin at Market Square; LS, 1821, Oct. 17, from Smallwood, forwarding the above letter to the Washington Common Council; and a ms. document, unsigned, agreeing that the corporation of Washington and the canal company will construct a basin at Market Square. Gelman Library purchased these materials in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Indenture, 05/23/1747 (Box 6, Folder 95)
    William Meriwether sells land in Hanover County, Virginia, to John Thomson, merchant. Printed form filled in by hand and signed by Meriwether and 3 witnesses. Gelman Library purchased this item in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Indenture, 07/28/1810 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    Ephram I. Hoyt sells to Suttle [sic] his Georgetown blacksmith shop and stable, with its iron and coal, for $75.00. Gelman Library purchased this indenture in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Document, 07/05/1794 (Box 6, Folder 97)
    Ship's paper (printed form) in French, English, and Dutch with manuscript inserts in English, for Henry Rust, Jr. for the brigantine Columbia. Signed by George Washington as President of the United States; countersigned by Joseph Hiller, Collector of Customs; witnessed by Edward Norris, notary public for the port of Salem, Mass. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Proclamation, 08/28/1998 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    Formerly ACC#734 This item is a proclamation by Mayor Marion Barry dedicating august 23, 1998 as the 35th anniversary of the march on washington day, schedules.
  - Indenture, 07/14/1826 (Box 7, Folder 99)
    The indenture arranges a loan of five thousand dollars for five years, with the church building and grounds as security, because of the church's "present pecuniary embarrassment." Gelman Library purchased this document in 1983. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Document, 02/08/1883 (Box 7, Folder 100)
    The document relays the appointment of William Fitch as Notary Public in the City of Washington, for five years; Signed by President Chester A. Arthur and Secretary of State F.T. Frelinghuysen. Gelman Library purchased this document in 1985. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Little Falls Mission M.E. Church under the auspices of the Dumbarton St. M.E. Chuch, 07/25/1871 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    Explains how the Dumbarton Street congregation organized to build a structure near Chain Bridge to replace one where services were held on the second floor. Lists members of the mission, contributors, trustees, and building committee. Gelman Library purchased this document in 2002. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Indenture, 09/10/1597 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    Indenture signed by Nicholas Overbury, father of sir Thomas Overbury (1581-1613). Accompanied by another unsigned indenture dated Sept. 26, in the 22nd year of the reign of Henry VIII. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - Letter, George Washington to Governor William Livingston, 06/18/1780 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    Postscript to a ms. letter of the same date, in the handwriting of Robert Hanson Harrison and signed by Washington; describes British ships at Sandy Hook, N.J., assumed to be carrying Sir Henry Clinton; conveys urgent need for more troops. Also within the box is a transcript of the letter from the book "The Writings of George Washington from the Original Manuscript Sources 1745-1799" edited by John C. Fitzpatrick. Formerly Ind. Ms.
  - History of 1925 F Street, N.W. Washington D.C., 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    This is an history of the building that houses the F Street Club, Washington, D.C. It was compiled by Mrs. Elden Billings, Columbia Historical Society. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 54.
  - A few notes on Hillwood, 04/1966 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    This businesswoman and philanthropist describes the rooms in her Washington home. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 52.
  - Foggy Bottom: this is how they lived, 06/24/1986 (Box 9, Folder 104)
    An architectural history of Square 43 in Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.), a triangular block bounded by 23rd and 24th Streets, G Street and Virginia Avenue. Written for a course at George Washington University, History of Washington, D.C. Mimi Minnick donated this document in 1986. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 51.
  - Force genealogy, 10/01/1931 (Box 9, Folder 105)
    Apparently by Edward Stead, grandson of William Quereau Force. Genealogy of the Force family, including biographies of Peter Force and William Quereau Force. Based on a paper by Cynthia Force Stead with additional information from Margaret Force Hunter. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 36.
  - William McLain Diary, 02/07/1834-12/16/1834 (Box 9, Folder 106)
    William McLain was a Presbyterian minister, pastor of First Presbyterian Church (Washington, D.C.), 1837-1840. In this holograph volume, McLain describes his pastoral work in small towns in New Haven Co., Conn.; his trip by steamboat and stage coach to see his dying father in Champaign Co., Ohio; his trip back to New York, stopping at Miami University and Lane Theological Seminary, and briefly at Washington, D.C.; his trip by steamboat from New York to New Orleans; and his pastoral work in New Orleans with mention of the controversy surrounding the pastorate of Joel Parker. Laid in the back of the volume are a 15 page ms. sermon and a 4-page pamphlet condemning ladies' corsets. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 15.
  - Field catalogue of transit stars, 1870 ca. (Box 9, Folder 107)